<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on genomics dev blog</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on genomics dev blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 13:17:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Nim Hts Example</title>
      <link>/post/nim-hts-example/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 13:17:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/nim-hts-example/</guid>
      <description>Several folks have recently expressed interest in learning nim which I have found to be very useful for genomics because it has a simple syntax like python, but it compiles to be as fast as C. In the case of mosdepth which is written in nim, it is faster than the competing C implementations because of choice of algorithm.
I have started using nim in my day-to-day scripting to replace python, in part, so this will be the first in a series of posts that show some relatively mundane code that I write like a script but will compile to run very fast.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You don&#39;t need to pileup</title>
      <link>/post/no-pile/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/no-pile/</guid>
      <description>I stumbled on this (now) obvious way of doing things that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen used much/at all; In a project soon to be released, we needed to quickly assay thousands of sites from BAM/CRAM files and do a sort of cheap genotyping&amp;ndash;or allele counting. Given this task, a common tool to reach for is the pile-up.
Pile-up is pretty fast but it has to do a lot of work. Even to assay a single site, a pileup will first get each read and a pileup structure (bam_pileup1_t in htslib) for each read into memory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Indexcov: cover your bases</title>
      <link>/post/indexcov/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Apr 2018 13:10:07 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/indexcov/</guid>
      <description>This post is to introduce indexcov and answer common question I get about interpretation.
I have found that, as indexcov is applied to cohorts approaching size of 100 or so, the probability that it will reveal something very interesting (either a data artefact or large chromosomal anomaly) approaches 1.0. For example, who knew that there were trisomies in Simons diversity panel?
indexcov quickly estimates coverage for whole genome BAM and CRAM files.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>mosdepth ideas</title>
      <link>/post/arrays/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Mar 2018 20:12:07 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/arrays/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m working on a new project and part of it is made possible by an observation that we stumbled on with mosdepth. It&amp;rsquo;s something that&amp;rsquo;s obvious in retrospect but wasn&amp;rsquo;t fully apparent to me until after mosdepth was mostly written. In short, that observation is computers can do stuff with arrays quickly.
The longer story behind that obvious and simple observation is as follows. mosdepth is a tool to calculate depth from BAM/CRAM files.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Smoove</title>
      <link>/post/smoove/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 16:49:22 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/smoove/</guid>
      <description>smoove wraps existing software and adds some internal read-filtering to simplify calling and genotyping structural variants. It parallelizes each step as it can, for example, it streams lumpy output directly to multiple svtyper processes for genotyping. It contains several sub-commands but users with cohorts of less than about 40 samples can get a joint-called, genotyped VCF in a single command:
smoove call -x --genotype --name $name --outdir . \ -f $fasta --processes 12 --exclude $bed *.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Noise</title>
      <link>/post/noise/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2018 19:35:37 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/noise/</guid>
      <description>This afternoon, I did a quick analysis to attempt to find variants on the X chromosome that are under recessive constraint&amp;ndash;that is that they appear in some non-zero frequency in females but never occur in male. That is, without an extra copy, a variant might be embryonic lethal in males, but could be seen in females thanks to a backup copy. I thought that these might be occurring at a relatively high allele frequency (greater than 0.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>