<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nim on genomics dev blog</title>
    <link>/categories/nim/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Nim on genomics dev blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2018 09:23:24 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/nim/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Nim to count sequence-motifs in a BAM</title>
      <link>/post/nim-mundane2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2018 09:23:24 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/nim-mundane2/</guid>
      <description>This is the 2nd post describing mundane uses of nim in day-to-day genomics.
The first post is here.
For today&amp;rsquo;s mundane task, a colleague asked me to count the occurence of 2 k-mers of length 39 in each of 603 BAMs of 60X coverage. We don&amp;rsquo;t care about partial matches or allowing mismatches so this is a pretty simple task. There are more efficient computational methods for this, but I wrote the simplest version, verified that it ran in &amp;lt; 2 hours for a single bam and then ran it overnight on a single machine with 64 CPUs and sent the results in the morning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nim Hts Example</title>
      <link>/post/nim-hts-example/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 13:17:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/nim-hts-example/</guid>
      <description>Several folks have recently expressed interest in learning nim which I have found to be very useful for genomics because it has a simple syntax like python, but it compiles to be as fast as C. In the case of mosdepth which is written in nim, it is faster than the competing C implementations because of choice of algorithm.
I have started using nim in my day-to-day scripting to replace python, in part, so this will be the first in a series of posts that show some relatively mundane code that I write like a script but will compile to run very fast.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>